<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>SRIJAN AGARWAL</title>
    <description>Web Developer, 19. I code, eat and write.</description>
    <link>https://srijancse.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="https://srijancse.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 16:58:53 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 16:58:53 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.1.2</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>FUDCon APAC Phnom Penh Cambodia 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was selected for delivering a talk on WikiToLearn at the FUDCon APAC, Phnom Penh, Cambodia from 4th to 6th November, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/fudcon.png&quot; alt=&quot;fudcon&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FUDCon (Fedora Users and Developers Conference) is an important event in the world of free software that is held in different parts of the world organized by Fedora Organization. The FUDCon comprised of sessions, talks, workshops and hackfest in which project participants worked on specific initiatives. FUDCon Phnom Penh was conducted at Norton University, Phnom Penh along Barcamp ASEAN. Around 50 speakers from around the world gave talks related to entrepreneurship and open source software. I was traveling with one my friends, Abhinand N, who also got selected to deliver a talk on Mediawiki. Looked like, we were the only two undergrads who were invited to deliver talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was my first international trip and pretty amazing. My itinerary was something like this : Cochin -&amp;gt; Kuala Lumpur -&amp;gt; Phnom Penh (4th November) and Phnom Penh -&amp;gt; Bangkok -&amp;gt; Cochin (9th November).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Phnom Penh looked more or less like an Indian city just with more &lt;strong&gt;prettier&lt;/strong&gt; girls (:D) and &lt;strong&gt;no&lt;/strong&gt; public transport. We reached Phnom Penh on 4th evening, and a tuktuk driver was waiting for us at the airport to take us to the hotel. If you’re wondering what a tuktuk looks like, see this :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/tuk-tuk.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;tuktuk&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As soon as we reached Hotel, it was almost Dinner time. Sirko Kemter was the local organizer and all the developers decided to go to a nearby BBQ place. Remember, Abhinand is a &lt;strong&gt;pure&lt;/strong&gt; vegeterian and he came to eat BBQ (:P). Anyway, the food was great, since I had never tried Lobster and Prawn. Amazing experience, it was.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the time of dinner, I interacted with rest of the Fedora developers from India, Australia, China and USA. &lt;a href=&quot;https://kushaldas.in/&quot;&gt;Kushal Das&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;http://sayanchowdhury.com/&quot;&gt;Sayan Chowdhary&lt;/a&gt; were among the famous open source developers from India. It was great meeting and interacting with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 1 : FUDCon APAC, Norton University, Phnom Penh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FUDCon Day 1 was pretty amazing. We started off with Barcamp pitches followed by &lt;em&gt;Fedora State of the Union&lt;/em&gt; talk from &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/User:Bex&quot;&gt;Brian Exelbierd&lt;/a&gt;, Fedora Community Action and Impact Coordinator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/brian.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;brian&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first talk I went to was &lt;em&gt;Introduction to Rust Programming Language by&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/a2batic&quot;&gt;Kanika Murarka&lt;/a&gt;. Kanika actively contributes to Fedora, and is an intern at Red Hat, Bangalore. She engrossed us, telling that Rust is designed to be a safe, concurrent, practical language, supporting functional paradigms and is sponsored by Mozilla.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/kanika.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;kanika&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lunch was pretty interesting. Everyone gathered at a common lunch place with full of local khmer snacks, jackfruits, veg fried rice and non veg rice. Veg food had egg in it, so yeah! (:D) Lunch was okayish, but what made it interesting was the discussion! I had a long discussion with &lt;a href=&quot;http://sumantrom.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;Sumantro Mukherjee&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/User:Pnemade&quot;&gt;Parag Nemade&lt;/a&gt; about my project and it was great! After the discussion, we followed for the next series of talks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/lunch.png&quot; alt=&quot;lunch&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next talk, I went onto was &lt;em&gt;How to globalize your software by&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/User:Pnemade&quot;&gt;Parag Nemade&lt;/a&gt;. Parag Nemade is a Senior Software Engineer at Red Hat. He is an active contributor to Fedora project, sponsor for packager group, proven packager, helps in improving Fedora packaging and testing Fedora updates. Parag introduced us to Globalization. It is a collaborative work done by internationalizing, localizing your software. He told us how important it is to globalize the code you write. Then he told what Localization is and how to add internationalization in code by showing some code examples. It was a great talk!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/paragn.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;paragn&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The following talk was by &lt;a href=&quot;https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/User:Aeng&quot;&gt;Alex Eng&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;Zanata, a translation platform&lt;/em&gt;. One of the best and interesting talk for the day. Alex presented a round up of the new features that will be available in the next release of the translation tool. I was very eager to learn more about how Zanata works, and therefore had a brief conversation with him. I was fascinated about the new editor and discussed  my GSoC project and collaborative editing would work in Zanata. Handling translations is very challenging and great thing is that, WikiToLearn is also looking for ways to implement Zanata.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/alex.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;paragn&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next talk was on &lt;em&gt;Web Virtual Reality&lt;/em&gt; by &lt;a href=&quot;http://sumantrom.blogspot.com&quot;&gt;Sumantro Mukherjee&lt;/a&gt;. The highlight of the talk was a-frame. A-frame is a web framework for building virtual reality experiences and works on almost all devices. With just few lines of code, you can turn a video into 360 degree Virtual Reality. Amazing, isn’t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/sumantro.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;paragn&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last talk of the day was by &lt;a href=&quot;anweshadas.in&quot;&gt;Anwesha Das&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;em&gt;A walk on licenses in Fedora ecosystem&lt;/em&gt;. She gave an overview of all the open source licenses, why it is important to use a license and what are the best practices of using a license. The take from the talk was not to use &lt;em&gt;personalized&lt;/em&gt; licenses and even if you use it, not to name it like &lt;strong&gt;Buy me a beer&lt;/strong&gt; or something similar. Overall, it was great to learn about Licenses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/anwesha.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;paragn&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The day ended with all the Indians and Ryan going to a Riverside Restaurant and having amazing food.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Day 2 : FUDCon APAC, Norton University, Phnom Penh&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming soon!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2016 13:13:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://srijancse.github.io/writing/FUDCon-PhnomPenh/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://srijancse.github.io/writing/FUDCon-PhnomPenh/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MediaWikiToLearn Hackathon, Amrita University Amritapuri Campus 2016</title>
        <description>
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 01 Oct 2016 13:13:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://srijancse.github.io/writing/MediaWikiToLearn-hackathon-auac/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://srijancse.github.io/writing/MediaWikiToLearn-hackathon-auac/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>MediaWiki Hackathon BITS Pilani Hyderabad Campus 2016</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I was invited by BITS Pilani Hyderabad Campus, to give a talk on WikiToLearn at the MediaWiki Hackathon on 24th and 25th September, 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was a great event indeed, and an amazing experience to speak about WikiToLearn among those students. I spoke on ‘How to contribute to WikiToLearn’ and the talk can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://slides.com/srijancse/wikitolearn&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few amazing things, I found out at BITS was :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;0% attendance requirements, creating nocturnal but hardcore engineers! Met crazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Soni&quot;&gt;Subham Soni&lt;/a&gt; waking up at 6 pm, like its 6 am. Met couple of others brushing at 20:00 in the washroom, getting ready for work.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Give students bad mess food, they would complain.
Give students good mess food, they would complain in a month.
Baffled at crazy &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/User:Soni&quot;&gt;Subham Soni&lt;/a&gt; addressing their mess food as boring/bad etc.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since, this was my first visit to Hyderabad, I also got an opportunity to roam around the city, with my BPHC Friends, Utkarsh and Utsav. Some of the photos :&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Visit to Charminar&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
 &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;/images/Charminar.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile image&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;BITS Pilani Hyderabad Campus&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
 &lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
     &lt;img src=&quot;/images/bphc.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile image&quot; /&gt;
 &lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Giving talk&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-wrap&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;image-block&quot;&gt;
    &lt;img src=&quot;/images/talk.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;profile image&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 25 Sep 2016 13:13:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://srijancse.github.io/writing/Mediawiki-hackathon-bphc/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://srijancse.github.io/writing/Mediawiki-hackathon-bphc/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Contributing to Open Source</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Since everyone was asking me this question regularly, I thought of writing a blog post of it. So, these are the points, once should be focusing on to crack Google Summer of Code or similar SoC programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Good understanding of one programming language of your choice&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Understanding of a programming language is not just knowing the syntax or how recursion works. If you already know that, great! You are past the first hurdle. Next, you need to take up the task of learning the multiple major libraries and packages that are going to be used in any medium to large scale project. Look up the relevant libraries of your programming language and devote time to learning them. A good understanding of these will go a long way in helping you understand any code base better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Version Control System&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes, this is where Github comes in. Distributed revision control(DVCS) is a way of collaborative coding which makes sure that all the code remains secure and concurrent at any given point of time. All, and I mean ALL, organisations use some form of Version Control. Major ones are SVN and Git. Although now mostly every organisation have switched to Git for some of its features, some might still be using SVN. Github is just a Git client which lets you host your code online. Learning Github is not the same as learning Git. Therefore, first, learn Git — Book then, moves on to learn how to use Github. For quick reference, you can also use this: Try Git Having familiarity with version control will give you quite an edge over other candidates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learn to read the source code&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is no substitute for the ability to read through seemingly gigantic code bases. Let’s face it, most of the documentation of any code available is very bad at the best. It may be useful to the end user, but for any new developer, it’s just gibberish. You are on your own when you need to go through the source code of something which spans hundreds of thousands of lines with hundreds of files. Where do you start? Well, it depends. Lear how to use Bug/Issue Trackers Every organisation will have a bug tracker. If you don’t know what a Software bug is, now will be a good time to start. Bug trackers are like the Version Co1ntrol systems which we talked about earlier. In fact, most version control clients will have an implementation of the bug tracker themselves. Github has an “Issues” system, which is the same thing. A bug tracker, basically, lists all the “issues”(or bugs) currently identified with the software and their “status”(are they solved? Unsolved? Being worked upon). Bug trackers provide the non-developer end users with a way of pointing out a problem in the software. They might also be used to request a new feature, which is different from a bug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Submit Patches&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve learnt all of the above(and trust me, it is not much), you are ready to submit some patches or bug fixes to a project of your choice. Choose any open source project which is written in a language you know, and more importantly, interests you, and go and browse through its bug tracker. Most bug trackers have issues marked as “volunteer” or “introductory”. Search for such issues, or go with any issue which you think you can fix. Comment/update the issue saying you are taking it up. Solve it on your local system (you’ll know what this is once you know how to use version control) and then push it to the organisation’s remote code base. This is easier said than done, let’s be honest. You’ll need to know at the very least, 1) What DVCS the project is using. 2) What are their workflows for code contribution? (Most organisations have a defined way to submit a patch and you &lt;strong&gt;MUST&lt;/strong&gt; follow that). 3) How to get involved with the community. Because even open source projects won’t accept unauthorised/unreliable code from some newcomer. More on this on the next point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Select an organisation/project and contribute&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This can come either after or before the last point. If you have no idea which organisation interests you, go to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://summerofcode.withgoogle.com/organizations/&quot;&gt;Google Summer of Code 2016&lt;/a&gt; and browse through the list of accepted organisation. Most organisations get accepted recurringly, so you are safe in picking an org which has been accepted 2–3 times already, filter according to the language of your choice. Once you’ve picked an organisation, start creating a good reputation for yourself. To do this,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1) Get in contact with the developers. Use &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.irccloud.com&quot;&gt;IRC&lt;/a&gt;, subscribe to the developer Mailing List of that org.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2) Submit patches. Nothing will help your case as much as your coding capability. Fix bugs. Even one is good. Start with the easiest of bugs. If in doubt, ask the devs to direct you to the bug they think will be good for you to start with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3) Get familiar with their workflow. This includes, how they contribute code, their coding style, if they hold any online meetings (do attend) etc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Ask (Smart) Questions&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once you are up and running contributing to a project, you &lt;strong&gt;WILL&lt;/strong&gt; face difficulties. You might not know how a particular piece of code is working, or you might not know about the required technology. This is the time for you to ASK. Ask the established developers in that project, or anyone you think who might know the answer, in general. Asking is not stupid and will see you through a lot of unnecessary struggle. But at the same time remember, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.catb.org/~esr/faqs/smart-questions.html&quot;&gt;How To Ask Questions The Smart Way&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is what you can do to lift your chances before the application period starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this helps you guys. Also, if someone wants to contribute to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.wikitolearn.org&quot;&gt;WikiToLearn&lt;/a&gt; can contact me anytime. :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 27 Feb 2016 13:13:39 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>https://srijancse.github.io/writing/contribute-to-open-source/</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">https://srijancse.github.io/writing/contribute-to-open-source/</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
